<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<notes>
    <subject>Web, HTML, &amp; CSS</subject>
    <overview>
        This chapter introduces the basic concepts on the Web, HTML, and CSS. Go over the notes and see how well
        you understand these topics by solving the given problem set.
    </overview>
    <topic>
        <title>WEB</title>
        <subtopic>
            <title>Basics</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    URLs of websites that handle private, important information, such as credit card numbers, often
                    begin with "https://".
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    HTTPS (Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure)  is the standard for transferring encrypted data on the web. It combines HTTP with the
                    Secure Socket Layer (SSL) and the more recent Transport Layer Security (TLS) cryptographic schemes
                    for securing communications and identification information over the web.
                </entry>
                <entry>HTML documents normally contain hyperlinks, which load a specified web document when clicked.</entry>
                <entry>
                    When the user clicks a hyperlink, a web server locates the requested web page and sends it to
                    the user's web browser.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Hyperlinks can reference other web pages, e-mail addresses, files and more.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    If a hyperlink's URL is in the form mailto:emailAddress, clicking the link loads the default e-mail
                    programme and opens a message window addressed to the specified e-mail address.
                </entry>
                <entry>URIs (Uniform Resource Identifiers) identify resources on the Internet.</entry>
                <entry>URIs that start with 'http://' are called URLs (Uniform Resource Locators).</entry>
                <entry>A URL contains information that directs a browser to the resource that the user wishes to access.</entry>
                <entry>Popular web servers include Apache's HTTP Server and Microsoft's Internet Information Services (IIS).</entry>
                <entry>W3C (World Wide Web Consortium) is a standards organization. Web technologies standardized by the W3C are called Recommendations.</entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
        <subtopic>
            <title>Servers Intro</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    A web server responds to client requests (typically from a web browser) by providing resources such
                    as HTML documents. When user enter a Uniform Resource Locator (URL) address into a web browser,
                    they're requesting a specific document from a web server. The web server maps the URL to a resource
                    on the serve maps the URL to a resource
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    A web server and a client communicate using the platform-independent Hypertext Transfer Protocol
                    (HTTP), a protocol for transferring requests and files over the Internet or an intranet.
                </entry>
                <entry>Any server that understands HTTP can receive a get request and respond appropriately.</entry>
                <entry>
                    HTTP status code 200 indicates success. Status code 404 informs the client that the web server could
                    not locate the requested resource.
                </entry>
                <entry>Two most common HTTP request types are GET and POST.</entry>
                <entry>GET request typically gets (or retrieves) information from a server.</entry>
                <entry>post request typically posts (or sends) data to a server.</entry>
                <entry>
                    A get request limits the query string to a specific number of characters.
                    Large amounts of information must be sent using the post method.
                </entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
        <subtopic>
            <title>Servers</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    To request documents from web servers, users must know the hostnames on which the web server software resides.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    The Apache HTTP Server, maintained by the Apache Software Foundation, is currently the most popular
                    web server. It’s open source software that runs on UNIX, Linux, Mac OS X, Windows and numerous other platforms.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Microsoft Internet Information Services (IIS) is a web server that is included with several versions
                    of Windows. Installing IIS on a machine allows that computer to serve documents.
                </entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
    </topic>
    <topic>
        <title>HTML5</title>
        <subtopic>
            <title>Fundamentals</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    HTML5 (HyperText Markup Language 5) is a markup language that specifies the structure and content of
                    documents that are displayed in web browsers.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    HTML enables you to create content that will render appropriately across the extraordinary range of
                    devices connected to the Internet.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Document Type Declaration: DOCTYPE is required in HTML5 document so that browsers render the page in standard mode.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Comments improves the documents' readability and maintainability. It starts with &lt;!-- and
                    end with --&gt;.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    HTML5 documents delimit most elements with a start tag and end tag. There are several so-called “void elements” that do not
                    have end tags.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    A start tag consists of the element name in angle brackets
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    An end tag consists of the element name preceded by a forward slash (/) in angle brackets.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Many start tags have attributes that provide additional information about an element, which
                    browsers use to determine how to process the element.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Each attribute has a name and a value separated by an equals sign (=).
                </entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
        <subtopic>
            <title>Elements</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    Title Element (&lt;title&gt; ... &lt;/title&gt;): The title element describes the web page. Titles usually appear in the browser
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    The title element is called a nested element, as it's enclosed in the head element's start and end tags.
                </entry>
                <entry>Search engines use the title for indexing purposes and when displaying results.</entry>
                <entry>
                    Paragraph Element (&lt;p&gt; ... &lt;/p&gt;): All text placed between the &lt;p&gt; and &lt;/p&gt;
                    tags forms one paragraph.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Heading Elements: HTML5 provides 6 heading elements (h1 through h6) for specifying the relative
                    importance of information. Heading element h1 is considered the most significant heading and is rendering
                    in the largest font. E.g., &lt;h1&gt; heading text &lt;/h1&gt;.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Image Element (img): For image rendering purpose. The img element's src attribute specifies an image's
                    location. Every img element must have an alt attribute, which contains text that is displayed if the
                    client render the image. Img element is a void element: e.g., &lt;img src = "cover.png" width = "90" height = "160"
                    alt = "best film cover" /&gt;.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Images are measured in pixels. Width and height are optional attributes; if omitted, the browser uses
                    the image's actual width and height. Although these two attributes are optional, always includes them
                    so that the browser can lay out the page properly even before it downloads the image.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    aside Element: It describes content that’s related to the surrounding content (such as an article)
                    but is somewhat separate from the flow of the text.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    The footer element describes a footer, the content that usually appears at the bottom of the content
                    or section element. E.g., &lt;footer&gt; footer content &lt;/footer&gt;.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Horizontal Rule &lt;hr/&gt;: draws a horizontal line that goes across a webpage as a thematic break
                    between paragraph-level elements. It's an empty element; it must have a start tag and be
                    self-closing (No end tag).
                </entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
        <subtopic>
            <title>New Input Types</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    To bypass validation, add the formnovalidate attribute to input type submit: e.g., &lt;input type =
                    "submit" value = "Submit" formnovalidate /&gt;.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    color: The color input type enables the user to enter a color. The proper format of a color input type
                    is Hexadecimal code.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    email: The email input type enables the user enter an e-mail address or a list of e-mail addresses
                    separated by commas (if the multiple attribute is specified).
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    date: The date input type enables the user to enter a date in the form in format yyyy-mm-dd.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    datetime: This enables the user to enter a date (year, month, day), time (hour, minute, second,
                    fraction of a second) and the time zone set to UTC (Coordinated Universal Time or Universal Time, Coordinated).
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    datetime-local: This enables the user to enter the date and time in a single control. The data is
                    entered as year, month, day, hour, minute, second and fraction of a second.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    number: This enables the user to enter a numerical value—mobile browsers typically display a numeric
                    keypad for this input type. The step attribute determines the increment in which the numbers increase.
                    The min and max attribute each sets the minimum and maximum valid numbers.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    search: The search input type provides a search field for entering a query.
                </entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
    </topic>
    <topic>
        <title>CSS</title>
        <subtopic>
            <title>Basics</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    CSS3 (Cascading Style Sheets 3) is utilised to specify the presentation of elements
                    separately from the structure of the document.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    CSS validator can ensure the code is correct and will work on CSS3-compliant browsers.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Inline Styles: Apply CSS property by declaring an individual element's format using HTML5 attribute
                    style.Each CSS property is followed by a colon and the value of the attribute; multiple property
                    declarations are separated by a semicolon
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Embedded Style Sheets: Writing styles and embed them in the head section of an
                    HTML5 document. This method separates presentation from content.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Linking External Style Sheets - link element: Uses rel attribute to specify a relationship between
                    two documents; rel attribute declares the linked document to be a stylesheet for the document. type
                    attribute specifies the MIME type of the related document; and href attribute provides the URL for
                    the document containing the style sheet.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    style element type attributes specifies the MIME type (the specific encoding format) of the style sheet.
                    For CSS style sheet, text/css is specified.
                </entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
        <subtopic>
            <title>New Features</title>
            <content>
                <entry>
                    Box Shadows: Apply shadow effect to any block level element in CSS3: box-shadow: x-offset, y-offset,
                    blur-radius, color;
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Rounded Corners: The border-radius property allows you to add rounded corners to an element. Any
                    border-radius value greater than half of the shortest side length produces a completely round end.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Color: CSS3 allows you to express color in several ways in addition to standard color names
                    (such as Aqua) or hexadecimal RGB values (such as #00FFFF for Aqua).
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    RGB (Red, Green, Blue) or RGBA (Red, Green, Blue, Alpha) gives you greater control over the exact
                    colors in your web pages. The value for each color—red, green and blue—can range from 0 to 255.
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    The alpha value—which represents opacity—can be any value in the range 0.0 (fully transparent)
                    through 1.0 (fully opaque).
                </entry>
                <entry>
                    Media Queries: The @media rule is used to determine the type and size
                    of device on which the page is rendered.
                </entry>
            </content>
        </subtopic>
    </topic>
</notes>